Hi everyone, today we're going to be
covering time series
analysis for social data. The
central idea of today's lecture is this.
In big social data
sets, time structure is not
a nuisance. It's part of the data
generating process. So if
you ignore time, you can build
models that look excellent in sample,
having things like high
R squared, low error, but
class and deployment. And even worse, you
can tell the wrong
causal story. So time is
not decoration and structure. Most big
social data sets are time
index. So examples of this
include platform logs, things like daily
active users, retention
engagement, online experiments
measured over days or weeks, economic
indicators like employment
or inflation, the event data
that's aggregated by day, and then topic
prevalence and texturing
for time. Now here's the key
principle. Time structure is not noise.
When something varies over
time, you must ask, is there
a trend? Is there seasonality? Is there
autocorrelation? Do the
measurement process change?
Do the population composition change? In
big data settings, time often
explains more structure than
cross-sectional differences. If you pull
across time without thinking
carefully, you're effectively
assuming that you have IID, which is
almost never true in social systems. So
there are three common
time index structures for time series. So
first we have time series.
This is one unit observed over
time. Example of these include things
like national approval, GDP, maybe total
DAU. Then we have things
like panels or time series
cross-sectional data. These are many
units observed over time. Examples of
this could be users by day, states or
countries by year or by week or by month.
And then we also have
event streams. These are irregularly
timed events. Things like this might be
tweets, protest events,
logins. But the key rule is that data
structure determines the model and
validation. If you have
one unit, you want to use ARIMA type
models, they make the most sense. If you
have many units, you
want to use fixed effects or hierarchical
models. If events are
irregular, you may need hazard models
or point processes. You don't choose
models based on taste, you choose them
based on their structure.
So there's extremely common and big
social data or repeated sampling over
time. So we have three
patterns. We have repeated cross-sections
for it. These would be things like new
samples each week or
weekly surveys. We have things like
rotating panels. This would
be things like respondents
process, some refresh for it, and then
rolling cohorts, so new
users each week. So these cause
different ability issues. And among them
are changes in outcomes, may
reflect composition change,
not behavioral changes. So what are some
examples of this? Suppose that there's
daily income averages
and they rise. Is this because people are
earning more or because high
income users are more active
that week? So this is especially
important in big data systems where users
churn, new users enter,
and measurement changes. So you have to
do some practical checks for this. One
way to do this is to
compare covariate distributions over time
or waves. You have to
post-ratify if your composition
starts to drift or you have to plot
cohort-specific trajectories. So this is
where a time series meets
causal inference. When you have many
units over time, you have
two dimensions. One is unit and
time. And as a base time workflow, we
have our Y sub IT, that's
our unit and our team for ISV,
I mean to be the experimental unit at
time t. And then we're going
to have an alpha parameter,
some sort of lambda parameter, then we
have our coefficients and
our epsilon in that case. When
we're doing standard regression, we
assume that our errors are
independently distributed, but we
know that there's a correlation in time
for our area. And so we have
to do some sort of, when we
have temporal data, we want to condition
out this issue for IID for
it. And in terms of this, it's
just serial correlation or errors for it.
So why does this matter?
If your standard errors are
wrong, then you're going to get a high
rate of type 1 error for
it. In big data sense, we have
serial dependence and it's almost always
guaranteed. So what are some problems
that we might encounter?
We have things like staggered treatment
adoption, dynamic effects for our time
series data, and then
feature leakage across time. Panel data
is a powerful way to try
to handle this, but only if
you respect our temporal dependencies.
So many big data science outcomes are not
static measurements,
they're durations. So standard of
modeling a level, we model how long until
something happens. For example, this
might be time until a
turn, time until first purchase, until
next login, or maybe until a
conversation or an event ends.
So what is a time to event outcome? A
time to event is a random
variable. The event could be,
like I said, churn, conversation,
purchase, it could be something like a
failure. In biomedical
sciences, we would use death for
criminology, we'd look at
something like re-offense or
protistoration for event data. In a big
data platform, almost
every retention metric is
fundamentally time to event. So one thing
that we might encounter
then is a term called right
censoring. Right censoring occurs when
you do not observe an
event before the study ends.
So example might be that a user, what a
user signs up, we've
observed them for 30 days,
they're not churned yet, we don't know
when they will churn. For
this would be two over 30, this
would be right censoring. In biomedical
sciences, maybe we want to
see how a drug intervention
extends life. People who live longer than
the outcome would be
right censored for this.
So then we have hazard versus survival
curve. So a survival function, we have
our time until event,
or the probability that event has not
happened before time t. For
a hazard function, it would
describe the instantaneous risk of an
event occurring at time t,
given survival to that point
for it. So for a survival, it might be a
churn for it, for example, a churn of
users. For a hazard,
an intuition might be among users who
have survived until time t,
what is the risk of churning
right now for it? So the key concept is
survival function
describe remaining probability,
a hazard function describes instantaneous
risk for it. As a key
understanding between
these, a survival curve is determined by
the hazard over time. So
high hazard early is our
survival drops quickly, and low hazard
means our survival declines
slowly. But if hazards change
over time, our effects are dynamic for
it. So what does it
matter in big data? Large
platforms often overemphasize static
metrics, ignore timing,
misinterpret early engagement
spikes. Survival modeling forces you to
think dynamically. And
dynamic thinking could be
necessary in things like retention
modeling, conversion
optimization, policy duration effects,
political mobilization timing, and
conflict onset timing. But it's just some
key concepts for this
we have our time to event outcome. It's a
variable measuring the
duration until an event occurs.
Right censoring is an event not observed
before the study ends.
Survival function or s, s of t for
the function is a probability that event
has not occurred by time t.
We have a hazard function,
is the instantaneous risk of an event
time t, conditional on
survival. And then we have time
varying treatment effects, which is the
treatment effects that
change over time. And it's visible
in survival curves. So here's just a
visualization what this
looks like. We have our survival
probability here, our turnover routine.
We see a decline in
survival probability over time,
and it's broken out by sex 1 and sex 2
for it. So we maybe we can just generally
assume that the blue
in this case is women, because women tend
to live longer for it.
Let's just say it's like a
biomedical thing. Yellow is below it, and
we see over time higher
risk of non-survival. The
interpretation would be higher risk of
non-survival over time where
your solo probability at this
point is like 25, but 4 and
much higher for the blue band.
So for forecasting over causal timing, we
have two goals for it. With forecasting,
you want to predict future values from
past values on it. And
then for causal timing,
we think about the estimated effect of an
intervention at a specific time.
But forecasting is generally going to be
about predictive accuracy,
or causal timing is about counterfactuals
for them. These are two
different targets. A model
can forecast well, but identify causal
effects poorly. In big data
experiments, we often combine
both. We want to forecast our baseline
and detect treatment
deviation, but never confuse
predictive accuracy with causal validity.
The biggest mistake we make generally,
we think about time, is data leakage or
time leakage in this
case. So time leakage happens
when the model sees the future before
training. So if we're trying
to forecast, we can't include
future data or forecasting efforts in it,
right? Because it'll
arbitrarily increase our predictive
power or forecasting power if it's
trained on future instances
of it. So you want to make sure
when you're doing something forecasting,
your training and test
splits don't break time ordering
because if they do, it'll produce an
inflated performance metrics for it.
So the correct evaluation is you want to
train the past and test the future
in forecasting efforts. If deployment is
forward looking,
evaluation must be forward looking.
This is one of the most common mistakes
in applied machine
learning for social science.
So a minimal assigned time series DGP can
be set up this way. We have
an animal DGP where we have
one sub t, we have our mu sub t and error
term here. This is an
inclusion for autocorrelation
in this case, but the key idea is
observations are dependent over time. We
include our autocorrelation
term here where standard errors are if we
ignore the autocorrelation
of time, these things are
a little bit wrong. Our inference is a
little bit wrong and our
forecasts are going to be wrong.
So this is a decomposition for trend
seasonality and residuals here. So we
have the same function
as before. We have Y sub t, T sub t plus
S sub t plus R sub t.
That's trend seasonality in our
residuals for it. So we have our original
time series here. We have our trend component. We have
our trend component. We have our
seasonality component and then our
residual component here.
But these are big data systems.
Seasonality is often
mechanical. You have to remove it before
interpreting your residual variation.
Otherwise, you're going
to attribute weekly cycles
to treatment effects for it. So here's
just a general visualization of
autocorrelated trend.
Autocorrelation is going to produce a
smooth looking data where we
have a sort of smooth trend
over time. So persistence in this case
does not imply signal. In
big data, many KPI share
strong autocorrelation. That makes that
regression look significant. But
significance makes reflect
mechanical persistence. This is why we
want to use like hack standard errors
and dynamic models can be more useful.
So proper forecasting evaluation, we want
to fit on T. We want to
predict on T plus one and then
slide forward and repeat this process.
This is going to
produce many out of sample
errors, but this would be a generally
useful way for
forecasting because it's not
leaking in future information for past on
it. And then we just
evaluate with our back testing.
So what does this look like visually? We
have our training data
in green here. This is I'm really now
very non colorblind
friendly. So we have our
yellow line or I'm sorry, our wine line
that's red here. We have our
training data here in green,
and then we have our testing data here.
And this is how we would
set it up where normally
if you're not concerned with forecasting,
just like maybe
increasing productive accuracy,
you wouldn't have to split your data by
training and testing over
temporally in this case.
So what would this look like as a
training testing window with back
propagation? We have
our training data here, we forecast here,
then we just slide forward
and repeat the same process
again for our back testing. So each of
these are just iterating for the blue
training with our time
T as our X axis. And our testing is
always going to be ahead of our training.
Ahead of our training data.
So even in randomized experiments,
outcomes are going to sit inside time
processes. We have big
N, but that doesn't remove things like
seasonality, drift, instrumental
instrumentation shifts,
spillovers, and randomization will solve
it doesn't randomization
just solve selection bias,
not these other problems for it. So we
want to solve our time
structure on it. So time series
can be even important if we are engaged
in experimental interventions.
So what is an interrupted time series? We
want to define a simple
causal timing for our design
where we have an intervention at T0. We
want to compare the pre and the post
while accounting for
trend over time. So this is what the
setup would be where we have our fixed
effects here and here.
We have our pre post treatment can be
things like some sort of policy
intervention, maybe a new
web page design for usage, maybe a
different headline. And
then we see differences in
let's say daily acted users depending on
the treatment of the new
interface for act maybe
the duration, differences in duration for
time pre and post.
And these are just ways
of modeling it with our T0 for that
intervention. Ways to check for to see if
there's a seasonality
or trend issues is doing fake
intervention data. So instead of having
it with actual implementation,
we just pick another arbitrary time we
test it again. And there's
a way for seeing if our data
actually has a trend for it. So if you
get statistical
significance when you pick an
arbitrary intervention date, it's a sign
that you need to account
for trends in your data.
And then also just generally
pre-trend diagnostic tests.
So here's an example of what inter ITS
intuition or interrupted
time series look like we have
a before intervention period and after
intervention period, we have
a measured outcome here. The
counterfactual is without the
intervention we would expect
for it to be here. So we see
a level change and then we see a change
here, which is just a
trend change over time. So we
have our intervention, our trend and our
estimated effect. Same here. And then
maybe here's another
example where we have our intervention at
T10 looking at T0 or
T20. Tobacco consumption,
this is our pre-intervention slope, our
post-intervention slope
for our policy intervention.
Maybe this is just some sort of like
discouraging or let's say this
is our new tax on cigarettes,
we would expect for the slope to continue
here, but the policy
intervention of this new tax would
be it is a decreasing tax for usage. And
then we can also just
look at the trends as a time
series for it where we have that shock
it's hit at T0 here
between maybe like around 120.
The intercept is lower and it becomes
higher after our intervention. So this
would just be a pre-post.
I'm just providing a bunch of different
visualizations how this might look
where we have our interrupted time series
for the observed versus
fitted versus counterfactual.
So the fitted line where we have our
observed data rather here
and here, going up, we have our
counterfactual without the intervention,
the red line, and then our
fitted for our interrupted
time series in here. So another time
series concept is a switchback
experiment. This is a
randomized experimental design and which
treatment assignment varies
across time blocks. So rather
than across individual units. So the
entire system is exposed to the same
random, the same conditions
during each block. So formally we would
have our Z sub T as an
element of 0 to 1, whereas Z sub T
indicates that the whole system is in a
treatment or control during the time
block T. So instead of
subbing, assigning Z sub I to individual
users, we assign Z sub T to time
intervals. So the intuition
of this is an environment with strong
interaction between units,
individual level randomization
causes interference. So one user's
treatment effect affects
another tree's use outcome.
So we have a market equilibria shift and
platform dynamics change. So switchback
experiment solved this by treating the
entire environment at once
during a time window. So the
core features of this is that we have a
unit of randomization,
which is our time block.
We have a unit of analysis, which is
system level outcomes or
user outcomes indexed by time.
The purpose of this is to mitigate cross
unit interference. And
then we have a structure with
alternating treatment and control over
time. So an example of
this might be from 9 to 930,
we have a control from 930 to 1030 of a
treatment from 10 to 1030 is
control. And then from 1030 to
11, it would be treatment. So why do we
use this? Switchback designs
are common when the treatment
changes the marketplace environment. So
supply and demand and
tract, network spillovers are
unavoidable. The system has equilibrium
dynamics. Examples of this
would be like surge pricing and
ride share markets, ranking algorithms to
where they're changing
our recommendation system,
marketplace fee adjustments, and then
congestion pricing experiments for it.
But the identification logic is the same.
Basically, we have
the treatment effect is
identified by comparing outcomes across
treated and untreated time
blocks. Because everyone is
exposed simultaneously, there is no cross
group contamination within a
block. But the key assumption
is that conditional on time trials and
seasonality treatment
assignment across blocks
independent of potential outcomes. This
requires randomized block
ordering, proper control for
time structure, no systematic alignment
with predictable cycles.
But just as a summary to
remember, the switchback experiment is a
randomized design that alternates
treatment and control across
time intervals, so that the entire system
is treated
simultaneously within each interval.
And this is going to reduce cross unit
interference and
interactive environments.
So here's maybe an example of the
switchback experiment
where we're going between
our control and our treatment mean and
then our treatment
blocks. So we have here,
and you can notice the variation
depending on our
blocking over time for it.
Okay, we're in a wrap up with talking
about sequential testing and peaking.
So the core problem is this in big data
systems, we rarely run a test
once and then check it once.
Instead, we monitor dashboards daily,
recompute P values
repeatedly, look at treatment effects
every hour, and then stop only see
significance. This behavior is called
peaking or sequential
testing without correction. So why does
repeated testing inflate
false positives? In class of
hypothesis testing, we assume that our
type one error is equal
to alpha. So in many cases,
it's going to be 0.05. This is true only
if we test once. If we test
repeatedly, the probability
of at least one false positive increases.
If we run k independent
tests at level alpha, then we
have at least one false positive is going
to be one minus the quantity
one minus alpha raise to k.
So an example, let's say we have our
alpha is 0.05. If we test 25
times, this becomes one minus
0.95 raise to the 20th or about 0.64,
which would mean there's a
64% chance of at least one false
positive, even if the null hypothesis is
true. So why does big N make
this work? We're smart sample
sizes, standard errors are going to
shrink, time differences become
statistically significant,
and noise appears meaningful. So
formally, we have our
standard error is going to be
tau hat is proportional to
one over the square root of N.
Some cases N approaches infinity, even
very small effect sizes
produce large case statistics.
So this creates a dangerous combination.
We have repeated testing issues,
very large N real time dashboards. And
the result is basically just
going to be you will almost
always find something significant under
these conditions. So
sequential testing occurs when
H don't as tested repeatedly as data
accumulates, instead of we collect a full
sample and test one.
So we do this, we collect some data we
test, we collect more data we
test again, and then we repeat
for this. The statistical properties of
tests change when the stopping time
depends on the data.
And this invalidates
naive p values for it.
There's just a minimal workflow we have
our data frame, we're
going to order a date,
we have test and training. In this
example, we're going to
fit a model in this case,
and then we're going to predict for our
left out time. And here's the same
code implementation where we're looking
at differences here
and our blue table facts
here and here for just an arbitrary
intervention. So as just a closing
reminder for time series,
error work is going to be sensitive to
the exact time for it
aggregation rules, missing
imputation and leakage for future
windows. So just always log
we'll have your split rule,
your data snapshot and your pre
processing choices. And then just keep these questions
in mind. So we're just telling the kids
happen in your own work,
what outcomes are most fragile
to instrumentation shifts, when you want
to do a B tests for time series problems,
and what makes a good
placebo test for temporal design.